Episode 1
Second Dish
Tohtsuki Culinary Academy:
（ナレーション）
遠月茶寮(とおつきさりょう)料理学園
a culinary bastion that continues to produce world-renowned chefs.
世界に名だたる料理人を
輩出し続ける美食の殿堂
Cooking in Progress
その高等部１年生を
対象として行われる―
Their high school first-years are contestants in the Autumn Selection,
〝秋の選抜〞は
今なお佳境にある
which is now reaching its climax.
Those who have survived
the preliminary round
予選を勝ち残った者たちは
次なる戦いに赴こうとしていた
are now preparing for the next battle.
（鳥の鳴き声）
POLAR STAR DORMITORY
All right!
（田所恵(たどころめぐみ)）よし！　んっ…
Did I pack the small knife?!
ぺティナイフ！
ちゃんと入れたっけ～？
あった！
There it is!
Did I pack the timer?!
タイマーは？
入れたっけ～？
ああ ああ…
Today is just an explanation of the main tournament.
（榊涼子(さかきりょうこ)）
今日は
本戦の説明だけでしょ
Do you really need your tools?
（吉野(よしの)悠姫(ゆうき)）
道具は
要らないんじゃないの？
ああ！　そっか
Oh, right.
Jeez. You never change.
もう 相変わらずね
Hey, Tadokoro.
（幸平創真(ゆきひらそうま)）おう！　田所
（悠姫･涼子）お…
Our ride's here.
（創真）
迎えの車が来たってよ
ああっ…
Let's go!
行こうぜ
The eight elites, all boasting impressive individuality and craftsmanship,
（ナレーション）
いずれ劣らぬ
個性と技巧を誇る―
精鋭８名が―
will wear themselves to the bone
to ascend to the top!
しのぎを削り
頂点を目指す―
秋の選抜本戦の幕が
今 切って落とされる
The Autumn Selection's main
tournament is beginning!
（小鳥の鳴き声）
WHAT FILLS THE BOX
Souma-kun, based on the lottery results,
（一色慧(いっしきさとし)）
創真君　抽選の結果だけど
創真君は第一試合から出場だよ
you'll be competing in the very first round.
The theme for the round is bento.
対決テーマは弁当だ
Bento?
（創真）
弁当って… あの弁当すか？
You mean a boxed lunch?
That's right.
そのとおり
You have the rest of the day to prepare for the match tomorrow.
今日中に必要な準備を済ませ
明日の本番に臨んでくれ
Bento, huh. This academy's more down-to-earth than I thought.
この学校 意外と庶民的なとこ
あるんすねぇ　お弁当なんて
（薙切(なきり)えりな）
フン　何を言ってるのかしら
浅学(せんがく)の極みね
What are you talking about?
You're ignorant to the extreme.
Bento is a food culture unique to Japan.
弁当は
日本で発達した独自の文化よ
Gourmands have long loved bentos created from high-end seasonal ingredients.
四季折々の高級食材による弁当は
食通たちに愛され続けているわ
Even prominent chefs overseas
are familiar with bentos,
海外の重鎮シェフにも
注目され―
and the word has even been added
to a French dictionary.
〝ベントー〞として―
フランスの辞書にも
載るほどなの
It is a highly appropriate theme
for a celebration of food.
正しく 美食の祭典に
ふさわしいテーマ
It's an entirely different beast from the B-grade "gourmet" food that you're so skilled at!
君の得意な低俗Ｂ級グルメとは
一線を画するものなのよ
ハハハッ
Gotta say, I'm not a fan of
that side of your personality.
やっぱ お前のそういうとこ
苦手だわ～
（えりな）なっ…
I'm pretty good at talking to people,
but man, Nakiri, you're something else.
俺 人と会話持たせるのは
得意なんだけど―
薙切 お前 よっぽどだわ
What?!
なっ…！
Things were pretty tense between us on our way back from camp too!
宿泊研修の帰りも
だいぶ気まずかったしなぁ
What's your point?!
何なのよ！　話の筋が見えないわ
何かイライラする～
I have no idea what you're getting at!
You're irritating me!
ふうん　珍しいね
薙切君が声を荒げるなんて
Oh, this is odd.
She doesn't usually raise her voice.
Ah, I have a visitor regarding an unrelated topic.
（叡山(えいざん)枝津也(えつや)）
おっと　ちょいと別件の客だ
俺は失礼する
Excuse me.
Yukihira Souma.
幸平創真
Try your best to make it through the rounds.
せいぜい気合入れて
勝ち上がってくれや
It'd be quite a downer if you were to fail in the very first round.
一回戦負けじゃ
場が白けるからな
So... who am I going up against?
んで 俺の対戦相手は？
THE 43rd AUTUMN
SELECTION
THE FOLLOWING DAY
GETTEN HALL
THE 43rd AUTUMN
SELECTION
Thank you for your patience!
THE 43rd AUTUMN
SELECTION
（川島麗(かわしまうらら)）
長らく
お待たせいたしましたぁ
THE 43rd AUTUMN
SELECTION
Welcome to the Autumn
Selection's main tournament!
秋の選抜 本戦
ただ今より一回戦―
We will begin with
the first match in round one!
第一試合を
開始いたしま～っす！
JUDGES
ACADEMY DIRECTOR
NAKIRI SENZAEMON
Our first contestant is Candidate Yukihira Souma,
who tied for second place in the Block A preliminaries.
まず登場したのは
予選Ａブロック―
２位タイで通過した
幸平創真選手
All right!
（水戸(みと)郁魅(いくみ)）おっしゃあ！
Good luck, Yukihira!
頑張れ～ 幸平～！
And his opponent is Candidate Nakiri Alice, who was the undisputed winner of the Block B preliminaries!
（麗）
そして その対戦相手は―
Ｂブロックをダントツの首位で
通過した―
薙切アリス選手です
（観客の歓声）
Nakiri Alice.
（タクミ･アルディーニ）
薙切アリス
Granddaughter of the Academy
Director, Nakiri Senzaemon,
（タクミ）学園総帥(そうすい)
薙切仙左衛門の孫娘にして―
and the grand champion of countless international competitions.
あらゆる国際コンクールの賞を
総なめにしてきた―
People call her the prodigy of molecular gastronomy.
分子ガストロノミーの申し子と
呼ばれる天才
予選で最高得点を獲得した
カレー料理は―
Her curry dish, which received the highest score in the preliminaries,
made use of cutting-edge
techniques and had a great impact.
最新技術の粋を凝らした
インパクトある品だった
How will you counter that, Yukihira?
どう対抗する 幸平
Yukihira-kun, today, I'll make your knees buckle with my cooking.
（薙切(なきり)アリス）
幸平君
今日は とろけさせてあげるわね
私の料理で
Wow!
（男子生徒Ａ）
すげえ　最新の調理器具だぜ
It's the latest in cooking equipment!
Even sitting in the audience,
I can feel the tingling tension on my skin.
（丸井善二(まるいぜんじ)）
観客席にいても
肌がピリピリするような緊張感だ
I can't believe he has to face one of the Nakiris in this atmosphere.
こんな中で薙切の一族と
やり合うなんて…
Yeah, I wonder how much pressure Yukihira is feeling right now.
（伊武崎峻(いぶさきしゅん)）
ああ　幸平 あいつ
どれだけの重圧の中にいるんだ
I deeply regret
ほ～んとうに残念だわ
that I'll only be able to see your cooking once on this great stage.
せっかくの大舞台で―
あなたの料理を
一回しか見れないなんて
俺に負けたら 二回戦から
客席で見れるじゃん
If you lose, you can keep watching my cooking from the audience.
Oh, I doubt that would ever happen.
それは無理だと思うの
Antiquated ideas and workmanship that rely on circus theatrics
曲芸頼りの職人芸と
古臭い発想だけでは―
are insufficient to best
the limits of culinary knowledge.
美食の英知を超えられない
ふああああ…
Oh, you didn't get a good night's rest?
（アリス）
あ～ら
昨日は眠れなかったのかしら？
Oh, I was up pretty late testing my dish.
いやぁ　結構遅くまで
支度しててさぁ
It was dawn before I realized the time.
気がついたら夜明けだったわ
But don't worry.
でも 心配は要らねえよ
This is just a normal day for me.
俺にとっちゃ
いつもの日常って感じだからさぁ
Foodie customers with high expectations,
舌の肥えたお客さん
ピカピカに研いだ包丁
shining knives honed to a razor edge,
and an array of ingredients...
ひとそろいの食材
The only thing that's different is that I have a formidable business rival in front of me.
いつもと違うのは 対面に
手ごわい商売敵がいるってこと
By beating you...
今日 あんたに勝って得るもの全部
俺の血肉にして帰るよ
I'll gain a lot today.
I'll use everything I gain
to grow even stronger!
On to the first match!
第一試合 お題は弁当！
Autumn Selection Main Tournament
The topic is "bento."
Round 1
Bento
The time limit is two hours!
制限時間は２時間！
Round 1
Bento
Let the cooking begin!
（薙切仙左衛門(なきりせんざえもん)）
調理 開始ぃ！
STANDBY ROOM
（観客の歓声）
Good luck, Souma-kun.
（恵）
創真君 頑張って！
（器具の作動音）
It's like watching a chemistry experiment.
まるで化学実験ね
丸井！　解説！
Marui, explain!
No, this is beyond the limits of my knowledge.
いや これは僕の知識を
凌駕(りょうが)している
Are those glasses just for show?!
その眼鏡は飾りなのぉ？
（アリス）うう～ん
This makes my Japanese DNA very happy.
私の中の日本人のＤＮＡが
喜んでいるわ
（創真）ん？
へえ～
なあに？
What?
Oh, you were making fun
of workmanship earlier,
いやぁ　職人芸をバカにしてたけど
腕は確かなんだなぁ
but you do have skills.
Of course!
当然よ！
How rude!
もう！　失礼だわ！
人のことをじっと見たりするなんて
You shouldn't stare at people like that!
I remember being stared at during camp.
俺も宿泊研修の時
ジロジロ見られた覚えが…
He's up against the director's granddaughter.
（男子生徒Ｂ）
学園総帥の孫娘が相手じゃな
Damn it!
くそぉ！　幸平
何か策を用意してるんだろうな？
Yukihira, you'd better have
some trick up your sleeve!
I bet he can win.
（タクミ）あいつなら きっと…
Finally!
（麗）
さあ 双方そろそろ
仕上がる頃です
It looks like both contestants
are just about done!
Who will finish first?
先に完成させたのは
薙切アリス選手です
It's Candidate Nakiri Alice!
Now, let's serve lunch.
さ ランチにしましょ
What?!
What is that?
何なの あれ
透明なドームの中に… 霧？
Is that mist under the transparent dome?
She's managed to make us wonder again!
くっ　想像を軽く超えやがる
Huh, there you go serving something weird again.
ああ～　また妙なもん
出してきたなぁ
（早乙女星周(さおとめせいしゅう)）
興味をかき立てる見事な演出
美食の祭典にふさわしい
What an excellent display. It piques one's interest.
It is entirely befitting for a celebration of food.
（観客のどよめき）
Temari sushi, is it?
手まり寿司(ずし)か
Yes.
はい
I used every technique I had at my disposal to create this temari bento.
私が持つ技術の粋を詰め込んだ
手まり弁当です
It's so beautiful!
なんと美しい！
Hm, the mist was liquid nitrogen.
（仙左衛門）
うむ　霧の正体は液体窒素
It also had the purpose of keeping the sushi fresh with the chill, I assume.
冷気によって寿司の鮮度を
維持する意図もあったか
If I may,
（アリス）
よろしければ このお弁当は―
I'd like to ask that you enjoy the contents in order, starting from the upper left.
左上から順番に
食べていただきたいのです
First, the bounties of the sea.
まずは海の幸
アワビの上にエスプーマ
There's mousse on top of the abalone.
That mousse is kelp stock.
そのエスプーマは
昆布のだしを泡にしたものです
The abalone was also wrapped
in kelp during preparation.
ネタのほうも
昆布締めにしてあります
（泡が はじける音）
By wrapping abalone in kelp,
（新戸(あらと)緋沙子(ひさこ)）
昆布締めにすることで
適度に水分が抜け―
you can get rid of excess moisture and prolong its freshness.
日持ちも よくなる
It's a method well-suited for making bento.
弁当に適した調理法ですね
You're right.
そうね
But I doubt that's the only reason for the kelp.
だけど 昆布の意味は
それだけではないと思うわ
（緋沙子）あ…
For that sushi,
（アリス）そのお寿司には―
I used bonito that has been aged for two days at low temperatures.
２日かけて低温熟成したカツオを
使っています
Hm...
うん
The umami is out of this world!
超ド級の旨味！
（大泉柿之進(おおいずみかきのしん)）
この旨味
カツオだけのものでは…
This umami isn't coming from the bonito alone.
カツオのイノシン酸と―
It's inosinic acid from the bonito
and glutamic acid from
the kelp used in the first sushi.
先ほどの昆布に含まれる
グルタミン酸
Those umami factors have a synergistic effect.
それらの旨味成分で
相乗効果が生まれているのです
This bento dish forms
a complete picture in your mouth
これは 順を追って
食べ進めることで―
口の中で次々と完成していく
お弁当なのです
as you eat each sushi in succession.
Wow.
（男子生徒Ｃ）すげえ！
（女子生徒Ａ）食べてみたい！
I want to try that!
It looks delicious.
（男子生徒Ｄ）うまそう
The second row is next.
（アリス）続いて２段目
They are a type of sushi that uses vegetables called "sushi cakes" in some circles.
野菜を用いた“ケーキ寿司”などと
呼ばれているものです
PUMPKIN
のりは一切使わず―
Nori was not used in these sushi.
Instead, paper-thin slices of vegetables are used to wrap the sushi.
野菜を薄く
ペーパー状にして―
BEET
包んでいます
NOZAWANA
このお弁当に
重い色は―
This bento has no use for heavy, dark colors.
ZUCCHINI
ふさわしく
ありませんから
And finally, the third row.
そして いよいよ３段目
This practically screams, "I'm the main dish!"
メインディッシュと
言わんばかりに…
It is aged beef fillet sushi.
牛ヒレによる
低温熟成肉寿司です
BEEF FILLET
（大泉）うーん…
また来よったぁ！
Here comes another wave!
２つの旨味成分が
口の中で広がっとるぅ！
The two umami factors just
spread through your mouth.
I can see where the inosinic acid comes from,
given that there's meat involved,
だが イノシン酸は肉寿司からと
理解できるが グルタミン酸は？
but what about the glutamic acid?
トマトですわ
Tomatoes.
トマト？
どこにも見当たらないが…
Tomatoes?
I don't see them anywhere.
It was a component of the sushi cakes.
（アリス）
ケーキ寿司に
含まれていたのです
遠心分離機を使って―
I used a centrifuge to separate tomatoes into pigment, fiber, and jus.
トマトを色素 繊維質
そして ジュに分解しました
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
Pigment
Fiber
Jus
The jus was filtered several times
to remove impurities.
さらに ろ過を重ね
よりピュアにしたジュを―
A few drops of that jus
was added to the sushi cakes.
ケーキ寿司に
数滴 落としたのです
I see!
なんと！
To think that the original ingredient was rendered completely invisible!
（審査員Ａ）
元の食材が
影も形もなくなるとは…
一番最後に残った品
Now, the last item.
What is the sphere nestled next
to the sea bream sushi?
（早乙女）
タイの寿司に添えられた球体は…
（仙左衛門）んん うん…
（審査員たち）んん！
The sphere...
（早乙女）この球体―
is concentrated stock!
だしを凝固させたもの
This is a sea bream chazuke that comes together on your tongue!
舌の上で完成するタイ茶漬けだぁ！
（観客のどよめき）
"The prodigy of molecular gastronomy."
（仙左衛門）
分子ガストロノミーの申し子
Her technique does justice to her moniker.
その二つ名に恥じぬ技術力で
味わう者の興をさかせ続けた
She was able to entertain her guests with her cooking from start to finish.
This deep satisfaction
その満足感たるや―
is as though we just enjoyed a feast at a luxurious traditional Japanese restaurant!
絢爛(けんらん)たる料亭の饗膳(きょうぜん)がごとし
（仙左衛門）うん！
小さな弁当箱から
美食の英知が―
This tiny bento box
roars forth such...
あふれ出よるわぁ！
culinary wisdom!
He's bared his chest!
（観客）おおー！
（男子生徒Ｅ）はだけたー！
There he goes!
（男子生徒Ｆ）出たぞ！
（女子生徒Ｂ）総帥の おはだけ！
The director's gone bare-chested!
Well done.
見事であった
ンフッ
This is Nakiri Alice's true strength.
（男子生徒Ｇ）
これが薙切アリスの実力…
How can such a chef be the same age as us?
（女子生徒Ｃ）
あんな料理人が同い年？
Even if I spent my entire life trying to reach her level, I never will...
（男子生徒Ｈ）
一生かかっても
追いつくことなんて…
（早乙女）
強すぎる才は
その光によって影をもたらす
When one's genius shines too
brightly, it casts a shadow.
因果なものですなぁ
That is her karma.
ここは遠月学園
この程度で萎縮する弱卒(じゃくそつ)は要らぬ
This is Tohtsuki Academy.
I have no need for weaklings
who would falter from this display.
見やれ
Look.
ん？
Five bentos, all done!
弁当５人前 上がり！
There's at least one chef who is not deterred.
萎縮しておらぬ料理人が
少なくとも１人
（仙左衛門）幸平創真 品目は？
Yukihira Souma, what is your dish?
のり弁っす
Nori bento.
What?!
（男子生徒Ｉ）何ぃ？
（男子生徒Ｊ）のり弁だとぉ？
Did he say nori bento?!
What?!
（女子生徒Ｄ）ええっ？
How can he possibly hope
to beat Nakiri Alice with that?
（男子生徒Ｋ）
そんな品で
薙切アリスに勝てるのかよ？
SOUMA'S NORI BENTO (ASSUMPTION)
（涼子･悠姫･郁魅）うわあ…
Nori bento?!
（男子生徒Ｌ）のり弁？
（女子生徒Ｅ）何それ
What the hell?
（男子生徒Ｍ）終わったな
He's finished.
Yukihira-kun.
幸平君
Huh?
あ？
What's a nori bento?
なあに？　のり弁って
What, you don't know?
あれ　何だよ 知らねえの？
I can make one for you later.
お前の分も
後で作ってやろうかぁ？
It's not just any nori bento, though.
ただ 普通ののり弁じゃねえけどな
（アリス）あ…
（創真）ゆきひら流 進化形のり弁
It's Yukihira-style Evolved Nori Bento!
Enjoy!
どうぞ おあがりよ
（審査員たち）おお？
They're called lunch jars.
（創真）
ランチジャーってやつっす
They're made of stainless steel and can retain the heat of rice and soup.
ステンレス製の保温容器で―
ごはんとスープの熱を
保つことができるんすよ
Hm? Japanese bento boxes are pretty advanced.
ふうん　日本のお弁当箱は
進んでるのねえ
More recent models can retain their contents' heat for up to half a day.
最近のは 半日くらいたっても
温かさが持つんだよ
Sides
Rice
Soup
Sides
Rice
Soup
If you heat up the soup before you put it in the jar,
スープを熱々にしてから入れると
ごはんの保温力も高まるし
it does a better job of keeping the rice warm.
Oh, how clever!
まあ！　賢いこと
Where's the tension?
（佐藤昭二(さとうしょうじ)）緊張感ねえなぁ
It's not like the match is over.
勝負の最中だってのに
She's being condescending toward Yukihira.
見下してやがるんだよ
幸平のことを
She's all smiles because she's convinced she'll win.
ニコニコしてるのは
自分が勝つことを確信してるからだ
Hm... First, there are three side dishes.
（審査員Ｂ）
うん　まずは… ３種のおかず
Hm!
おお　すばらしい磯辺揚げ
見事に揚がっている
This fish cake fried with nori is amazing!
I made the fish cake from scratch.
そいつは魚から作った
自家製ちくわの磯辺揚げっす
He used beer in the batter.
衣にビールを使ったのね
Alcohol is more volatile than the batter,
アルコールは
水よりも早く揮発するから―
so it becomes light and crispy.
ベタつかない軽い食感になる
Huh?
うえ？
涼子 何で知ってるの？
How do you know what he did, Ryouko?
I saw Yukihira-kun testing his dish at the dorm last night,
（涼子）ゆうべ 寮で幸平君が
試作しているのを見かけて―
so I asked for a taste.
ひと口 味見させてもらったの
Oh!
ああ！
So much umami's bursting forth!
すごい旨味があふれてくる
磯の香りが…
I can smell the sea!
（犬）びゃう！
I'll envelop you.
（磯部(いそべ)磯兵衛(いそべえ)）包み込むで候
Wh-Who are you?
だ… 誰？
（審査員Ｂ）うーん
The kinpira-style sauteed burdock also has a mellow, deep flavor.
（審査員Ｂ）
きんぴらごぼうも
まろやかでコクが深い
I've added just a bit of mayonnaise and balsamic vinegar as secret ingredients.
隠し味にマヨネーズと
バルサミコ酢を―
わずかに加えてるっす
I see.
なるほど
細部にまで こだわった仕事ぶりだ
You were very meticulous with this dish.
Oh!
おお！
Look how easily the chopsticks
cut through the fried cod!
タラのフライが 箸で軽く切れよる
The cod must've been first simmered in stock and seasoning before it was fried.
恐らくこれは だしと調味料で
一度煮てから揚げているな
That step gave it its soft, flaky texture.
そうすることで
ふかふかした柔らかい食感に
あむ
What?!
（大泉）何ぃ！
（大泉）
アッハハハハハ～
アッハハハ　ア～ハハハハハ…
What a pure, mild flavor it has!
透き通るような まろやかな風味
It is like a gentle highlands breeze!
高原に吹く 柔らかな風のよう！
What refined flavor!
なんと上品な味なのだ
一体これは？
Where is this coming from?!
（仙左衛門）
その答えは だしにある
The answer to that question
can be found in the stock.
これはマグロ節(ぶし)による だしだ
This is dried tuna stock.
That's right.
そのとおり
The cod was simmered in stock made from dried tuna and rishiri kelp.
タラを煮た だしはマグロ節と
利尻昆布から引いたものっす
Dried tuna...
マグロ節…
That would've been made from yellowfin tuna.
キハダマグロを原料とした
節類ですね
Yes.
ええ　カツオだしと比べると
淡泊だけど―
While it is not as rich as bonito stock,
it has a very delicate and elegant umami.
非常に繊細優美な
旨味を持つ
Cod also has a light umami,
so the dried tuna is a perfect match.
淡い旨味が特徴のタラは
マグロ節との相性もバッチリ！
What a light dish!
何とも軽やかな一品だ
The soup is next!
次は汁物
Oh!
おお！　ベーコンと玉ねぎの
みそ汁か
It's bacon and onion miso soup!
Ah, this too...
おお！　これもだ
（審査員たち）アハハハ…
The unique fragrance
of the tuna stock fills your nostrils.
（審査員Ａ）
マグロだし特有の かぐわしさが
鼻腔(びくう)を抜ける！
Combined with the meltingly sweet onions,
玉ねぎの とろりとした甘さも
相まって―
it's as though the soup envelops your entire body!
体中を包み込むようだ～！
Also, there is a trick
to taking advantage of this bento box.
ちなみに この弁当箱を生かす
スープの裏技がありまして―
Just by putting the stock, ingredients, and seasonings in the container,
保温容器に だし 食材 調味料を
放り込んでおくだけで―
you can have a sweet soup a few hours later.
The vegetables will be cooked through.
数時間後には
野菜に じっくり火が入った―
甘いスープになるんす
Oh, that's useful.
ふうん　便利なものだわ
ハッ　今日はすぐ食べるから
火を通してあるけどな
Today, there won't be any time delay,
so I've cooked the ingredients already.
You know a lot about bentos.
詳しいのね
お弁当のこと いろいろと
Sure. I've made them at my family's diner.
まあな　実家の定食屋でも
作ったことがあるし
But that's not enough, Yukihira-kun.
でもダメよ 幸平君
Your efforts are all too conventional.
どの工夫も普通すぎ
Even bentos should be full
of spectacular surprises.
お弁当といえど 華やかな驚きに
満ちた品でなくっちゃ
Just like my temari bento.
私の手まり弁当みたいにね
Yeah, yours did look really tasty.
確かにお前の
すげえうまそうだったよなぁ
あ 今度食わせてくれよ
Let me try it sometime.
ウフフ　もちろんいいわよ
Yes, of course.
But was your dish really amazing as a bento?
（創真）
だけどさ お前の品って
ちゃんと弁当として すごいわけ？
What did you say?
何ですって？
I'm asking you what we should
be putting in bento boxes.
（創真）
俺たちが あの箱に
詰めるべきものは何なのかって話さ
One of my diner's regulars
was a granny called Kiyo-san.
うちの常連に キヨさんっていう
ばあちゃんがいたんだ
She came almost every day,
毎日のように来てくれてたのに―
but one day, she hurt her back and couldn't come.
ある日 腰を痛めて
来られなくなっちまってさぁ
（チャイムの音）
Hello?
（キヨ）あ はいはい
Granny Kiyo!
キヨばあちゃん
腰 大丈夫か？
Is your back okay?!
Souma-chan, isn't your diner busy right now?
創真ちゃん
お店が忙しい時間じゃ…
（キヨ）あいたたた…
（創真）あっ
Ow...
Here you go!
はい これ！
What?
え…
You haven't had dinner yet, right?
（創真）
晩ごはん まだだろ　んじゃ！
Later!
（戸の閉まる音）
（キヨ）わざわざ届けて…
You came here just to deliver this?
（創真の息遣い）
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
（創真）
“店がメチャクチャ べらぼーに
ヒマだったから作ってきた”
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
The diner was super empty,
so I made this for you.
Eat it up and get better!
“これ食って 元気になれよ”
P.S: Lift up the nori before eating the rice!
“ついしん”
“ごはんを食べる前に
のりをめくってみて！”
Eat it up and get better!
P.S. Lift up the nori before eating the rice!
（キヨ）ああ…
Now you're going to taste what
I was trying to deliver...
（創真）
あの日 俺が弁当箱で
届けようとしたもの…
in that bento box back then.
お前も味わってけよ
The flavors...
おいしさと その先にあるものを
and what lies beyond!
What?
うおお…
What is this rice?
何じゃ このごはんは…
I-Is this...
こ… これが…
のり弁だと言うのか？
...really nori bento?!
ふんっ
ああっ…
There are strange black grains on top of the rice.
（大泉）
何やら黒い粒が
ごはんの上に敷き詰められておる
What's that?
（男子生徒Ｎ）何だ あれ
（女子生徒Ｆ）キャビア？
Caviar?
Salmon roe?
（男子生徒Ｏ）イクラか？
（女子生徒Ｇ）黒い…
It's black.
How curious!
何とも面妖
だが 食べずにはおれん
Nonetheless, I must try this.
Knock on wood!
南無三！
どううばあ！
It feels like salmon roe
bursting in your mouth!
イクラのような食感が
はじける～！
What gushes forth
from within is the umami of nori!
中から しみ出すのは
のりの旨味だぁ～！
（観客のどよめき）
The nori's salty umami goodness bursts forth to coat each grain of rice.
はじけた のりの
うまじょっぱさが―
ごはん一粒一粒に
まとわりついてっ…
I can't stand it!
たまらん！
病みつきになりそうだぁ
It's addicting!
You made those spheres
by extracting the nori's umami
それは のりの旨味を
抽出し―
and adding sodium alginate
and potassium chloride.
アルギン酸ナトリウムと
塩化カルシウムによって―
球状形成したもの
Molecular gastronomy!
分子ガストロノミー？
But that's...
それって…
...Nakiri Alice's specialty!
薙切アリスの得意分野！
How do you know this technique?
（アリス）
どうしてあなたが この技術を？
The other day, Isshiki-senpai invited me to help out at a kids' cooking class.
こないださぁ
一色先輩に誘われて―
子供料理教室ってやつを
手伝ったんだよ
Huh?
はあ？
I got to be buddy-buddy with the kids.
子供たちと仲よくなってさぁ
At the end of class,
they gave me snacks and stuff.
最後にお菓子とかを
もらったんだよなぁ
One of the snacks
reminded me of something...
その中の１つを見て
思い出したんだ
Pop-A-
Spheres
When I was a kid, I'd tried one of these.
Pop-A-
Spheres
ガキの頃
俺も試したことがあったなってね
Pop-A-
Spheres
What?
なんと！
A cheap candy product?!
駄菓子か！
What are you talking about?
だがし… って何？
This is one of those so-called educational snacks.
こいつは いわゆる
知育菓子の１つ
ああ…
Potassium chloride and sodium alginate...
（アリス）
塩化カルシウムに
アルギン酸ナトリウム
It's a snack that lets you make artificial fish roe.
人工イクラ作りを
体験できるってやつだ
I was really into it as a kid.
子供の頃 ハマってさぁ
いろいろ試したんだよ
I played around with it quite a bit.
Look, Dad!
ほら 親父　みそ汁 固めた！
I made miso soup solid!
Wow, that's cool.
（幸平城一郎(ゆきひらじょういちろう)）
うっは！　面白(おもしれ)えなぁ
But don't ever serve that at our diner.
でも店じゃ出すなよ 絶対
These black beads are nori umami bombs
（創真）
この黒い粒は 味つけのりを
俺なりに進化させた―
that I made from seasoned nori.
のりの旨味爆弾ってわけだ
He thought of a molecular gastronomy
technique from a cheap candy product?
分子料理のエッセンスを
駄菓子から思いつくとは
Hm?
ん？　ごはんの中に何やら…
There's something else in the rice...
んん…
ふお～！　風味満点！
So much flavor!
It's dried tuna simmered down in soy sauce!
マグロ節で作った佃煮(つくだに)だ
It was a four-layer dish!
四重構造になっておったかぁ
If Nakiri Alice's dish was
a meticulously-arranged jewel box,
薙切アリスの品が整然としつらえた
宝石箱だとすれば―
this nori bento is a treasure box full of marvels waiting to be discovered!
この のり弁当は
さながら発掘を楽しむ宝箱！
It reminds me of my field trips and picnics as a child.
幼き日の遠足で…
（審査員Ｂ）行楽で…
That excitement
when I'd open the bento box...
（早乙女）
弁当の蓋を開けた時の…
（審査員Ａ）
あの高揚感が…
It's all coming back to me now!
（審査員たち）
よみがえるようだ～！
My temari bento even included a finishing dish: the sea bream chazuke!
私の手まり弁当には
締めのタイ茶漬けまでついていたの
The overall taste quality was higher in mine—
総合的な おいしさは
私のお弁当のほうが…
ああ ストップ
Oh, please stop!
Can you leave about one-third of the rice?
ごはんを３分の１くらい
残しといてくれますか
There's yet another compartment under the very first lid.
一番上の蓋の裏
もう１つ 容器を仕込んであるっす
It's kudzu sauce!
葛あんか
That kudzu sauce has three times more dried tuna and rishiri kelp than normal.
（創真）その葛あんには―
マグロ節と利尻昆布を
通常の３倍量 突っ込んだ
Pour it over the piping hot rice and dig in.
こいつをほかほかごはんに
かけていただく
Let's finish up.
締めといこうぜえ！
Of course that's...
（審査員たち）そんなもの！
...going to be...
うまいに…
...delicious!
（審査員たち）決まっとるー！
ううう… 葛あ～ん
Ah, kudzu sauce!
It's so good!
たまりませんなぁ
Combined with the nori bombs...
のり爆弾と合わさって…
また格別の旨味…
...it's a whole new level of flavor!
Those judges...
審査員のじいさんたち…
They're eating like they're really having fun,
（青木大吾(あいきだいご)）
薙切アリスの時とは
打って変わって―
unlike when they were eating Nakiri Alice's dish.
何か すげえ楽しそうに
食ってるなぁ
Yukihira-kun.
幸平君　お弁当に詰めるべきは
心だとでも言うつもりかしら
Are you trying to make the point that bentos should contain "heart"?
What's important is the flavor, isn't it?
大事なのは
美味であるかどうかでしょう？
Don't get all "mind over matter" on me—
精神論なんかで…
No!
否！　精神論ではないな
アリス
It's not about that, Alice.
Grandfather!
おじい様！
はっ！　いつの間に
おはだけに？
When'd he get bare-chested?!
Alice, your bento took advantage of the cold.
アリス お前の弁当は
冷気を生かしたものだったなぁ
Yes, because bentos should be chilled.
（アリス）ええ　だってお弁当は
冷めるものですもの
Yukihira Souma didn't get fixated like that.
（仙左衛門）
幸平創真は そのようには
決めつけなかったぞ
（アリス）はっ…
（仙左衛門）
彼は まず弁当の外側に
目を向け―
He first thought about the bento container,
then filled it with entertainment
whose flavor was enhanced by warmth.
温かさで おいしさを生かす
エンターテインメントを詰め込んだ
That's what this bento is.
それが この弁当だ
Of course, your dish
was delicious in the extreme.
もちろん お前の品は
極めて美味だった
But wouldn't you say that you could've served the same dish
だが 例えば寿司対決であっても
同じ品を出したのではないか？
if the theme had been sushi?
あっ…
You merely used your skills to fill that box.
（仙左衛門）
お前は 持てる技術を
あの箱に当てはめただけに過ぎない
There are flavors that can only be communicated through bento.
弁当だからこそ
伝えられる おいしさ
There are creative techniques you can devise to advance bento culture.
弁当文化を進歩させる工夫
Bentos can be fun
and innovative in their own way.
弁当としての楽しさや新しさ
Did your dish capture any of that?
お前の料理には
それがあっただろうか
Well, sure... but what's important is the flavor.
まあでも 大事なのは
うまいかどうか
（アリス）あっ…
I don't disagree with that.
（創真）
そこに関しちゃ異論はないぜ
Dig in, Nakiri Alice!
おあがりよ 薙切アリス
（アリス）んっ…
ああ…
Alice-sama, you look well.
（男性Ａ）
アリス様 ご機嫌麗しゅう
How is Erina-sama?
（女性Ａ）
えりな様はお元気ですか？
Please give Erina-sama my regards.
（男性Ａ）
ぜひ えりな様に
ごあいさつを
Erina-sama.
（男性Ｂ）えりな様を
（女性Ｂ）えりな様
Erina-sama!
（男性Ｃ）えりな様
（男性Ｄ）えりな様
Erina-sama.
Erina-sama!
Erina-sama...
（女性Ｃ）えりな様
Father, I would like to go to
your research lab in Scandinavia!
（アリス）
お父様！　私もお父様の研究所に
北欧へ行きたいです！
Please take me there now!
今すぐ連れて行って！
お願い！
What's cutting-edge... the most advanced...
（アリス）最新 先鋭…
I must gain weapons that are mine alone, so that I won't lose to Erina.
えりなに負けない私だけの武器を
I can't lose to anyone...
えりなに… 勝つまで
誰にも… 負けられないのに…
before I win against Erina, and yet...
うっ はあ…
（２人）うん
Bring me the brush!
筆を持てい！
ぬおおおおああ！
（アリスの泣き声）
あ…
It's so warm.
あったかい…
うっ うう…
ああ～！
Round one, match one!
一回戦 第一試合　勝者は―
The victor...
Yukihira
Souma
is Yukihira Souma!
Yukihira
Souma
幸平創真とする！
Yukihira
Souma
Glad you liked it!
御粗末！
He won!
（観客の歓声）
（悠姫）勝った～！
Woohoo!
（観客の歓声）
フッ
Yukihira!
幸平！
Miss Alice...
アリスお嬢が…
Yukihira, you're really interesting.
（葉山(はやま)アキラ）幸平…
お前 ほんと面白えよ
♪～
omoiegaiteru imeeji yori haruka mukou gawa e
Far beyond the image I have in my mind
tsukuriagete yuku shinjitsu wa mada tooku
The reality I'm building up is still far away
hatenai tabiji
An endless journey
otagai no puraido wo togisumaseyou ze
Let's hone each other's pride
kotoba nante kazari wa
Words aren't really important
hai dakyou saseba ii
So let's just say "yes" and leave it at that
butsukariai migakarete iku
We fight each other and hone our skills
No reason
deai wa shockwave shockwave
Our encounters cause shockwaves
mada shiranai sekai e
We're reckless challengers
arukihajimeta mubou na chousensha sa
Heading toward a world as yet unexplored
kenshi ga yaiba de ashita wo
A swordsman should use his blade
kirihirakeba iin darou
To open the way to the future
dareka no mon ja nai jibun dake no story
This is my story and no one else's
Cause we are still rough diamonds on the road
～♪
（観客の歓声）
（恵）創真君
Yukihira
Souma
Souma-kun.
Yukihira
Souma
Wow!
すごい　すごいよ！
You're amazing!
（ノックの音）
あ…
The second match is about to begin.
（女子生徒Ｈ）
間もなく第二試合です　準備を
Please get ready.
Oh, o-okay.
あ… はっ はい！
Charm for
Academic Success
It's my turn next!
Charm for
Academic Success
次は 私の番！
Charm for
Academic Success
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
Standby
Room
Candidate
Kurokiba
Ryou
NEXT TIME
THE INTERPLAY OF LIGHT AND SHADOW
Next time: The Interplay
of Light and Shadow.